{"tossups": [{"question": "An attempt to dissolve this alliance ended at Rotebro when king Hans captured the peasant leader Sten Sture the Elder. This alliance was weakened when the Engelbrekt Rebellion managed to unseat Erik of Pomerania in favor of Christopher of Bavaria. The 1523 coronation of Gustav I Vasa marked the end of this alliance, which was constructed by Margaret I and Haakon VII in order to challenge the Hanseatic League. For ten points, name this medieval union of Denmark, Norway, and Sweden.", "answer": "<b> Kalmar</b> Union (or the Union of<b> Kalmar</b>is)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This city\u2019s skyline features two cranes, known as \u201cSamson and Goliath,\u201d in the shipyards of Harland and Wolff. Its neighborhoods of Short Strand and Cluan Place are separated by a \u201cpeace line,\u201d as are Falls Road and Shankill Road. The<em> RMS Titanic</em> was built in this city, which was home to a parliament at Stormont which was dissolved during the height of the Troubles. The Good Friday Agreement was signed in, for ten points, what city, the capital of Northern Ireland?", "answer": "<b> Belfast</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "The Raiders came back to defeat this team in the 1968 \u201cHeidi\u201d Game, whose ending was cut off on television by a children\u2019s movie. This team won its only Super Bowl by a score of 16 to 7 against Earl Morrall and Johnny Unitas after the quarterback guaranteed an upset victory. Joe Namath is the all-time leading passer for this team, the winner of Super Bowl 3 over the Baltimore Colts. For ten points, name this NFL team that shares the Meadowlands of New Jersey with the New York Giants.", "answer": "New York<b> Jets</b> (prompt on New York) Page 2", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This country was targeted by the Aberdeen Act, which authorized the Royal Navy to board its ships. A period of regency in this country led to a series of independence revolts, such as the Ragamuffin War. During the Peninsular War, Prince Regent Joao moved his monarchy to this country. It fought the Platine War against Argentina and was part of the Triple Alliance that defeated Paraguay. For ten points, name this country that gained its independence from Portugal after the Treaty of Rio de Janeiro.", "answer": "Empire of<b> Brazil</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "One novel by this author sets scenes at a tavern named The Boot, which was used by the participants in the Gordon Riots. Another novel by this author is partially set at Satis House, inspired by a mansion of the same name in Kent, where the widow Miss Havisham lives; in that novel, a convict who is sent to Australia makes a fortune and becomes the benefactor of Pip. For ten points, name this British author of serial novels like<em> Barnaby Rudge</em> and<em> Great Expectations</em>.", "answer": "Charles<b> Dickens</b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "During this event in 2015, 107 people were killed by a crane collapse, while a stampede in 1990 killed over 1,400 participants. This event commemorates the seeking of water by Hajar, who ran between the hills of Safa and Marwah seven times; that path is now enclosed by the Masjid al-Haram. Other rituals that take place during this annual event include<em> tawaf</em>, in which one walks around the Kaaba. For ten points, name this pillar of Islam, requiring an annual pilgrimage to Mecca.", "answer": "<b> hajj</b> (prompt on descriptions of pilgrimages by Muslims to Mecca)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "At one point, this man\u2019s base of power was the North American city of New Castle. This man was imprisoned in the Tower of London for writing the tract<em> The Sandy Foundation Shaken</em>, and, while in jail, he further angered his captors by penning the anti-monarchist<em> No Cross, No Crown</em>. He incorporated principles of his faith into a<em> Frame of Government</em> for a colony he founded. For ten points, name this Quaker who oversaw the planning of Philadelphia in a state that now bears his name.", "answer": "William<b> Penn</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Projects along this river include the Elephant Butte and Amistad Dams. The mouth of this river was once home to the port of Bagdad, which was heavily used by the Confederacy. A swing bridge spanning this river connects the cities of Matomoros and Brownsville, and it was claimed as the southern border of a republic that gained its independence after the Battle of San Jacinto. For ten points, name this river that serves as the boundary between Mexico and the State of Texas.", "answer": "Rio<b> Grande</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "Leo Amery attacked this man in Parliament by quoting Cromwell\u2019s \u201cIn the name of God, go!\u201d speech. This man was forced to resign after the failure of the expedition to Norway. He declared that there would be \u201cpeace in our time\u201d after signing the Munich Agreement, part of his policy of appeasement towards Nazi Germany. For ten points, name this British prime minister who was succeeded by Winston Churchill at the beginning of World War II.", "answer": "Neville<b> Chamberlain</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>According to Ammianus Marcellinus\u2019 account of this battle, Bacurius led the Scutarii, who fled like cowards after leading an early, unordered charge. That acccount also details how, after this battle, the losing commander fled to a (+) cottage, where he was burned to death by enemies unaware he was hiding inside. This battle could have been avoided with an armistice proposed by (*) </b> Fritigern. For ten points, name this monumental 378 AD defeat of Emperor Valens, a Gothic victory that doomed the Eastern Roman Empire.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Adrianople</b> (or<b> Hadrianopolis</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>Alfred Kempe\u2019s false proof of this statement was exposed in 1890 by Percy Heawood. When applied to toroidal graphs, this statement has an upper bound of 7. This theorem was</b> <b>proven by Kenneth (+)</b> <b>Appel and Wolfgang Haken, who used the University of Illinois\u2019</b> <b>resources to study nearly 2,000 cases in which different maps may have violated it. The first widely-accepted \u201cproof by (*)</b> computer\u201d was for, for ten points, what mathematical theorem regarding the number of colors required to shade a map without adjacent regions sharing a color?", "answer": "<b> four-color</b> (map) theorem (\u201dcolor\u201d is not needed after said)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Math"}, {"question": "<b>For one post, this man was selected over William Paterson as a replacement for Oliver Ellsworth. John Adams claimed that the \u201cproudest act of my life\u201d was gifting this man to</b> <b>the American people. This man (+)</b> <b>changed a previous tradition of delivering opinions</b> <em><b>seriatim</b></em><b>. In one decision, he argued that a writ of mandamus could not be issued because the Judiciary Act of (*)</b> 1789 was unconstitutional, thus establishing the power of judicial review. For ten points, name this third Chief Justice of the Supreme Court the author of the opinion in<em> Marbury v.</em> <em>Madison</em>.", "answer": "John<b> Marshall</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This leader returned to power four years after a leaked speech revealed that the MSZP, his country\u2019s Socialist Party, lied \u201cmorning, at noon, and at night\u201d about its ability to govern. In 2014, this leader proposed \u201cillberal democracy\u201d and a governing style more</b> <b>like (+)</b> <b>Turkey or Russia. 44% voter turnout stymied this Fidesz Party leader\u2019s 2016</b> <b>referendum opposing EU migrant quotas, a year after this leader built a barbed wire fence on his country\u2019s southern border with (*)</b> Serbia. For ten points, name this current Prime Minister of Hungary.", "answer": "Viktor<b> Orban</b>  (1) <b>This man\u2019s forces slaughtered the Swiss Guard as they defended Clement VII</b> <b>during a sack of Rome. Nobles angry at this man for appointing officials from his</b> <b>native Flanders rebelled in the Revolt of the (+)</b> <b>Comuneros. His admiral Andrea</b> <b>Doria lost the Battle of Preveza to the rival Ottoman Empire and he captured his</b> <b>other rival Francis I at the Battle of (*)</b> Pavia. This man oversaw the conquest of the Aztec and Inca by conquistadors. For ten points, name this Habsburg Holy Roman Emperor and King of Spain. ANSWER:<b> Charles V</b>, Holy Roman Emperor (accept<b> Carlos I</b> of Spain or<b> Charles I of Spain</b>, but don\u2019t prompt on Charles I alone; prompt on Charles or Carlos)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}